okay so I I'll restart because I was
muted so uh folks this is the last
lecture of the class so I will keep it
short maybe 20 minutes or something and
after that we'll uh turn it over for
open discussion and we'll have a
recording of the formal part of the
class the first 20 minutes the lecture
and after that we'll have a discussion
which will be free form so that will not
be recorded so uh let me just hit on
this topic because this is important and
uh uh let
see
uh okay so uh we start with a very basic
observation and this is really an
observation not about any robotics task
but about human
behavior so it's well known that human
behavior is hierarchical and has many
levels so the earliest example I could
find of this in the literature was from
this book from 1954 I mean there is uh
in the AI literature there's something
called the general Problem Solver GPS
which is like late 1950s and literature
on planning but I thought I found this
this book which was about human behavior
that they studied in like a small
Midwestern town just observing what
people do and and there's this example
where uh if you think of this uh like
seven-year-old girl who's going to
school right so you can think of first
if you think of the action at the SEC
level of 1 second A to B she's stepping
down from the Cur so imagine that she's
working from home to school okay then
there is the action of crossing the
street right then there is the action
there's a bigger this is a step in a
bigger action which is walking to school
then well she wants to graduate from
third grade okay that so you need to go
to your classes and then there is a
higher level goal which is getting an
education and then as abstract as you
can get climbing to the top of
life okay but in all human activity and
human behavior we can construct these
hierarchies I mean the canonical example
that people use in the AI literature is
about if I want to fly from here to
Boston if I want to go and give a talk
at MIT what do I need to do there will
be steps which are you know me walking
to the front of the building taking an
Uber walking inside the airport getting
on a plane getting off the plane and so
on and so forth right so we we have
activities at the lowest scale which are
the steps that I'm taking while I'm
walking to the goal of uh getting
walking out of this room and avoiding
obstacles to the goal of taking uh
getting into an Uber and we can continue
so there are always multiple hierarchies
of action of human behavior so when we
go to a robot it has to be the same
there is no choice if robots are going
to help humans they are going to be
helping us with various tasks and all
tasks will be hierarchical in
nature okay uh now how do we think about
these tasks so I have uh this slogan
which I like which is action equals
movement plus go so every action that
you perform we can think of it in two
spaces there is the physical space I
mean the space of uid and newon where we
are moving and we move because we apply
forces and muscles contract and so on
for a robot there are motors which apply
torqus to join and so forth so there is
the space of movements
right okay but these movements are
purposive they are not random they are
in order to achieve
goals okay so one of the goal of that
seven-year-old girl is to climb to the
the ladder of success in life at some
level I'm sure she's not thinking of
that she's probably just thinking of the
fact that her mom has told her that she
needs to go to school but uh goals exist
at all levels uh so like I mean uh the
the goals are hierarchical and then the
movements in order to achieve them are
also hierarchical but whenever you
observe an
action always think of it as having a
dual
identity there is the identity in the
space of uid and Newton physical
movements which translate to change in
pixels and so forth and then there is
the more abstract story of what is this
in the service off and there's a plan
and goal and it's not one or the other
it's very important to note that you'll
often find people you'll get into
discussion where people are missing the
point and they'll focus on one or the
other no both are equally important
right okay and uh and this uh you can
can put in context by just thinking of
the notion of planning and models at a
More abstracted Level so again I I found
this this very old quote this is 1943
this is even earlier than my previous
quote so this is from Kenneth Craig is
the little book he wrote which is If an
organism carries a small scale model of
external reality and of its own possible
actions within its
head okay it is is able to try out
various Alternatives conclude which is
the best of them react to Future
situations before they arise utilize
their knowledge of past events and so
on okay this is a description of the
planning process but it is because
planning is thinking through what
sequence you
will act on before you actually act on
it
right you need to do some planning is
what you do before you actually
act right and then and this needs a
small scale model of external reality
and now this term model can be
interpreted in many different ways I
mean there is the the models of control
theory people which is uh essentially uh
there is a state x and x at time t + 1
equal F of XT and U subt so U subt is
the control input you apply the XT is
the state at the previous time and then
there's some function which transforms
it to the next to the state at the next
moment of time and there are equivalent
versions of that which if you construct
a a linear model then you can do a x
doal ax plus Buu and this is the where a
is a matrix X is a column Vector B is a
matrix U is a column Vector x dot is a
column vector and if you know the
derivative then you can of course go
from XT to XT + one right and then often
in this kind of model you have that you
you actually have uh some observables Y
which are related to the state it's not
the complete state but some observables
from that so the this these are you
should think of these as different
mathematical
formalisms which are trying to get at
the idea that CRA is doing CRA is
proposing today we there's a lot of uh
usage of the term World models I mean uh
which uh for example Yan Lun has talked
a lot about uh in terms of uh for vision
Robotics and so on but it's exactly this
idea okay and this idea is a very good
idea it's fundamental we have to have it
okay there's no no it's not like
debatable there are things which we
debate but this is not worth debating
this is just correct
uh the devil is in the details after
that right what is the nature of the
models at what level of the hierarchy
are they how do we acquire them we have
to solve the learning problem of how do
we acquire these models all of this has
to be
done okay uh I I want to now uh get to
this equation actually equals movement
plus gold but I'm going to talk about it
in a different way which is essentially
about the role of words and the role of
pixel Els
okay so uh okay so this is uh the I mean
the book Harry Potter I mean it's been
absorbed into all these llms so in fact
you can ask any of your llms you know
chat GPT gpt3 gp4 Lama Gemini whatever
you can ask it these questions and
you'll be able to get those answers
right so this is the level of language
okay but is language complete as a way
of capturing the phenomena that we care
about and for me the answer
is when you watch this
movie does I mean I hope most of you
have watched this movie right is there
anybody who hasn't watched this movie
okay I won't embarrass you I assume
everybody watch this stovie
okay because I had a young child had to
watch it multiple times so okay uh okay
and sorry
uh and and this is the book
right the book is
not and and the movie are correlated
they're telling the same story but they
tell it in different ways a great
novelist
describes things in a certain way with
words a great movie director makes the
same story but with pictures with pixels
so the there are words inside JK Ring's
book those are the tokens there and then
the tokens here are fixel right one is
not superior to the other they are both
important they're both important and
they are correlated but not exactly the
same that's why we even after you read a
book you want to go watch the movie
right okay now let's connect this back
to this action equals movement plus
goal of these when you watch the movie
what is most
obvious the movement right the movements
you see them the pixels convey the
movements so the movement part is much
more evident in the movie and if you are
watching a movie with the sound off and
no subtitles you can certainly observe
all the movements what you miss out when
you don't have listen to the dialogue or
the goals when you can infer a lot of
that but it helps to have the dialogue
so the goal part is e easier in language
because in language we can describe like
a novelist can describe the mental
thoughts of a of a character in a movie
Steven Spielberg can't show the mental
thoughts of the person he has to find a
way to to for the characters to perform
actions or
reveal their inner State through
movement right but both both I'm trying
to say a thousand times it's not one or
other you need both and when you think
about approaches to robotics you will
need both so people when they say oh
llms can do everything they're missing
the point because language models are
very good at capturing the more abstract
aspects which will be the goals and
plans but not necessarily good at
capturing the the
movement okay so let me now uh with this
background to set the mood let me talk a
bit about long Horizon planning and I've
just like this one slide I could have
gone into more detail but I think this
is fine so I want to do it as a little
history lecture first so the the use of
planning in AI the earliest example is
actually this GPS this General so-called
General Problem Solver but in the
context of Robotics is this robot called
shaking okay and what you f should do
when you have the time is go to YouTube
and search for shaky the robot so shaky
the robot was developed at SRI so near
Stanford around 1969
7071 and Nils Nelson was one of the main
people behind it and they in that
project they realized that they needed
to solve the planning problem
and they came up with a formalism for
solving the planning problem and that
idea has stuck around and that idea is
essentially to have operators which have
some preconditions delete lists and add
lists so there's a paper from like 1971
which has all of this and uh let me
maybe let me illustrate that and I will
uh the folks on Zoom will miss this
because I'm going to use the board and
because I didn't have a slide for it but
uh
let's so uh the example that they used
that the shaky robot uh that they used
for the shaky robot was uh was
essentially about uh stacking blocks on
a table so you have some
table okay and then you have some blocks
so so think of this as little cubes
okay and let's call this let's call this
block a and Block B okay so suppose so
what do I want to achieve and then maybe
I have a third
block okay and let's call this Block C
so there are three blocks on a table and
now I I State my goal and and this was
all done using predicate calculator so
logic so the goal that was uh that
suppose I have is on
a and on b
c and on C comma
table okay so this is the
goal okay how do I achieve this goal
okay I need some operators what are the
operators so you can have an operator
which is
pickup you can have an operator which is
put
down right and this takes some arguments
right so these will have some arguments
like X and Y I would specify them so so
then what do I have to do if you think
about this plan it's a kind of Tri plan
I pick up B I put down B on C then I
pick up a and then I put down a on top
of B these are some steps which are
involve pickup and put down and I will
assemble the the tower now of course I
could have some initial condition and I
could have an initial condition where
block a is on top of Block B and C is
there now in fact in order to achieve
that goal first what I have to do is to
remove a from on top of B so I have to
take a step which is going in the wrong
direction then move B on top of c and
then move a on top of B I mean if like a
standard program in exercise of the
towers of Hanoi where you have to do
this sort of stuff anyway you get the
flavor so what they had was logical
operators which had some
preconditions and then some add list and
delete list add list are what are facts
that will be true after the operator has
been executed and delete list will be
what facts are no longer true and
everything is specified using
logic okay and then uh so what is the
planning process the planning process is
you have some initial state so it fits
into this mode of world model and states
and so on right there's a state in
there's an initial State and then you
have a series of this application of
these operators pick up and put down
with different arguments and then you
get to an end state where we have uh the
following uh characterization on ab and
on BC and on c
table okay this is how many years ago
this is like uh 55 years ago right okay
and then this area has built up there's
a AI planning Community which is not
which is broader than robotics I mean
you can talk about this if you're
planning a mission to Mars right or or
or building a factory I mean there are
many many settings where what we have
are there are tasks and they have
dependencies and you need to do task uh
tasks X before you do task Y and so on
right all of this if the framework is
one which can be where the operators can
be expressed in logic then this
classical Paradigm applies and modern
versions of it there is this language
called
pddl okay which is which is for uh
describing plans and then and then there
is a search involved in finding these
plans but but we can do that I mean this
is all quite
tractable okay now uh let's
consider these ideas carried over into
into uh into Robotics and a very leading
example of this is the work from Tomas
loano perz and Leslie Keling called Tam
which is Task and motion
planning so task and motion planning the
task planning part is very much like uh
this old tradition from uh uh the logic
folks from shaki and onwards so very old
tradition uh MO planning has to do with
the geometry of the world so if I want
to pick up so so this for the logistic
people pickup is a Elementary operation
pick up a
block but for a roboticist this is not a
trivial operation because you have to Mo
move the robot arm to the right place
you have to make sure you don't collide
with any object you need to have the
right grasp for picking up that object
so so this inside this pickup is a lot
of
sort of Robotics uh expertise that is
needed and and that's what they captured
with this idea of motion planning where
motion planning for them you was usually
assuming that you have complete
knowledge of the state and you are
you're you're really solving this
problem of collision avoidance when you
have a multiple degree of Freedom it's
quite reasonable uh what are the
challenges so one challenge always is
this always this problem that we have in
logic Frameworks versus the real world
is because in in the real world we
perform actions but things go slightly
wrong the state is continuous in nature
and logic Frameworks are not very good
at handling that okay so that's one
problem the other is that suppose we
want to take this idea and want to apply
it for General general settings right I
want this I want my robot in my home and
it should be able to do my housework it
should be able to clean the floor it
should be able to tidy the children's
bedroom it should be able to cook meals
it should be able to do laundry fold
laundry etc etc okay what's the
challenge that you see here the
challenge here is we have to design all
these
operators right designing all these
operators and how many of them are there
are there a list of 50 is this a list of
100 is this a list of thousand It's
actually an open world it's
unbounded so
this is where I think language models
come in because language models have a
lot of implicit knowledge of the world
that they have acquired through this
simple task of next token prediction so
inside gpt3 or gp4 you actually have
knowledge of all these
operators right they are there I mean so
I gave an example of making an omelet
somewhere in there there would have it
would have read some recipe books and so
forth so therefore it has knowledge of
okay you must break an egg and you must
stir it and you must do this and you
must do that kind of knowledge is there
in
llms right so operators knowledge of
operators is is there in the llms and we
can draw on it and we should draw on it
so there's a simp good way to think
about that what's missing what's missing
often is that these these models are not
necessar very good at logical reasoning
they're making good guesses but they're
not not good at logical reasoning so
they can come up with plans which are
actually incorrect but uh but if we
found ways of combining the llm type uh
Machinery with a sort of the more uh
logical inference type Machinery we
would have the best of both words this
isn't there yet but it will be there
sooner or later I think one
instantiation of this idea is the idea
of outputting a program and then
executing the program because your llm
can output a program so a program is
really the same as a plan there's not
much of a difference between plans and
uh plans I mean I I talked about a plan
with operators but if you think about a
program that you write in a programming
language like C or or Pascal or python
or whatever I mean you have operations
right each statement is an operation
they have argument it's really the same
thing like the pickup operator it's the
same game so therefore uh the
realization has to be that if you can
out if you are outputting a program
you're outputting a
plan and now what you want to do is some
kind of checking is this is this correct
is this is this executable and so on and
then we might imagine a more logic type
machinery for that part so I want to uh
leave it at that and not not get too
hung up on the current usage of these
llms because often they are not
necessarily used the right way but in
the long run there will be a role for
llms and they will be in providing
operators and we will need some process
maybe the llms will be the error rates
will come down enough that you don't
need to check but very likely you may
need to
check so uh let me pause here and ask if
you have any questions on this
okay and now what what is language not
good
for okay I have a couple of slides which
I want to argue that language is not
good for certain things and and this is
essentially to do with uh the role of uh
how much spatial reasoning is present in
LMS so this is a paper from some
colleagues at Apple you can find this on
archive it's I like this paper a lot and
uh I want to give a context for it which
is couple of years ago we had a uh at at
like one of the cbpr there was some
debate and the other and this were and
at that time vladin colon was very much
was very excited by lens and very much
in the mode that I mean computer vision
and Robotics can all be
solved by llms and they will all they I
mean that may be an exaggeration and in
fact part of the and the and the the
claim comes from the following which is
a legitimate argument that these llms
are bringing in a lot of knowledge of
the world through the words so so the
claim would be you build a word model
but you've implicitly got a world model
for free that would be the thesis and as
such that's a it's a plausible claim so
now you have to test it and and the way
you can test it is by various kinds of
spatial reasoning tasks so there are a
bunch of spatial reasoning tasks which
come from the psychologist so these are
the kinds of tests which show up in you
know IQ tests and so forth so for
example there some object and you have
to rotate it and guess how it looks like
from another Viewpoint there is some
Maze and you have to find a path from
the start to the end and so on and so
forth and what we can do is to try uh a
some kind of VM I mean this has this has
to be a model which can take in pixes as
input and see how good they are at this
and they did these they did a bunch of
these tasks and they tried a variety of
these models GPT 40 GPT 4V etc etc and
these were multiple choice questions and
the Chance performance was 25% and most
of the models were like close to chance
and humans are very good at it so at
least current models have not solved the
problem of spatial cognition and they
had two versions of it spatial reasoning
in the large and spatial reasoning in
the small small is more about like
rotating objects and guessing how they
are from different points of view uh
large is more like okay I am at a
certain position there's some other
person who's sitting Northwest of me at
7 m there's some other person who's
sitting Southeast south or just south of
that person at 12 M what's the
orientation of that person with respect
to me things like that right which is
very easy reasoning with geometry of the
type that any high school kid knows
right and even if they haven't studied
it in Geometry they can just answer this
from their intuitive spatial reasoning
but these models can't so that's that
sort of an argument uh eventually
whether we will have multimodal LMS
which will be able to answer
this I hope so but they will come when
we have treated the spatial reasoning
part of the problem with due
respect I think the current models are
largely language models with a little
bit of uh Vision thrown in and usually
that Vision part is basically that they
have recognition of the you recognize
the scene and now you've got tokens
corresponding to the objects and so
there like a bag of words model
and there people are pushing this
technology they are trying to put in
more spatial information but it's fair
to say that it isn't quite there yet but
a few years down the road well that
branch of adding in spatial information
into these models as it advances we
might do better that's totally
okay and then I want to conclude with
this uh story so uh this is these are
instructions on how to climb a staircase
okay let me move this out so you
can okay let me put it here so it
doesn't bother you so I'll let you enjoy
reading this for a few
minutes it's from this author called
Julia
cazar
okay so this is how you you teach a
person to how to climb a stair
Casas okay and if this is how you try to
teach your three-year-old child how to
climb a staircase I don't think you will
have much luck it is much better to do
this as I said you can talk about
climbing a staircase or you can climb a
staircase okay and my point is climbing
a staircase is easier than trying to
pass that that that that those set of
words so uh okay so but the so I I
usually use this as a line mainly to win
arguments against these the people who
are big fans of llms that language is
not quite the right way to capture
skills I mean we have low-level robotic
skills like picking up throwing walking
climbing and these skills are in the
space of joint angles and movements of
joint angles and perception with from
pixels and so on and and that is needed
okay and words that don't capture that
but I don't want you to make the other
mistake which is to say that words are
un important words are important words
are important for capturing
high level goals and plans right like
why did this robot want go climb the
staircase right things like that right I
mean I think those are those are uh
those are equally important and we need
to have this balanced view okay I'll
stop here and I think we can uh if there
any question